hey everyone, welcome to my zz tutorial
大家好,欢迎观看我的zz视频教程
this video is part one
本视频是此系列视频教程的第一集
and in this part I'm going to be showing you guys
本集讲向你展示下大概的zz解法
as well as some background information
还有些历史背景
so there will be 4 things in this video, and this video will be more of a sit back relax and listen type of video
本集主要讲四点,你只要舒服坐着看就行了
there wont be too much movement, nor there will be too much strictly  educational content
没有太多的魔方操作,也没具体的解法
it's mostly really interesting information and some stories
大部分都是些有意思的东西和故事
the first thing what  I'll do is I'll get you guys a break down of the method
首先要讲的就是此魔方解法的大概过程
so I'll explain verbally what the method is all about
我会口头讲解下此解法
what happens in the method
解法的过程
the second thing I'll do is give you a quick demonstration solve
第二部分是实例演示
so you can actually see what happens
这样你就能看到到底此法是如何还原魔方了
in the zz solve
此法名为zz
I will give you the mothod's history
此法的由来
as well as interesting background information
一些有意思的东东
the last thing is I'm going to talk about my experience using it
最后是我的经验
so let's get into the breakdown of the method
那就开讲啦-- zz解法的大概分解
so let's talk about a little bit about  the method's breakdown
zz分解就是说它的每个步骤
so when I say breakdown I mean what steps are in the method and in what order to become
以及直接的衔接
so the zz mothed has three steps the first step is called the OE line
so the zz mothed has three steps the first step is called the OE line
EO stands for edge orientation, so you can expect there will be  some sort of magic with edges
EO是指边块色相还原,由此可见在开始还原时
before you start actually solving things
会有些边块色相转化操作
and the line obviously refers to a line-like structure on the cube
line就是线的意思,指的就是魔方的两相对边块
in this case , it's a line on the D face
比如这个,就是底面(Down)的这条线
so whatever is down for you
底面是什么色看你的偏好了(译者:我是蓝底红前,国际配色)
and it's built between the front center and down center and the back center
这条线就是这三个块: 前底,底面中心块,后底
so it's this line right here
看到没?这条线
in the demonstration solve, I'll show you guys excactly what  an EO line looks like
等下的实力演示我会让你看清楚这条EO线
but for now, it's ..edge's all oriented, and then there's a line that solved over here
那么现在嘛.. 边块色相都对了, 这里有条线
you can think of it as  a  half cross if your background is CFOP
如果你用的是CFOP解法的话,你可以把它想象是个半个"十字"(译者:我是啊)
after the EO line is finished
EO线这步骤完成后
the solver ago ahead and does F2L
就要解第二步:　 F2L(前两层）
and the F2L feel very very different, because the edges are oriented in the first place
这里的F2L很特别,因为这个时候所有的边块色相在一开始都对了
in our case the F2L is render three (joint?)
这样F2L就只要"三相操作"就行了
and what three (joints?) means is solvable by using only three different face turns
三相操作意思是说只要转动三个面就可以完成F2L前两层
and in our case the face turns are RUL
这三个面就是R(Right右面), U(Up顶面), L(Left左面)
so you can use any form of R moves, like R' R2 or even R itself
这三面可以随便转动,比如可以R(右面顺时针转动) R'(右面逆时针转动), R2( 右面转动180度,哪个方向?都可以啊)
and any form of U move, and any form of L move, and those three moves or type of moves or groups of moves are the only moves needed to solve the F2L
顶面和左面也是,只要是能解F2L的操作,这三面随便转
so because you only have three different type of moves, you dont have to retate the cube
因为只要转动这三面,所以都不需要整体转动魔方,很顺手不是吗(译者:这个等下就说到了)
becaue you can reache RUL all from this position, you dont have to do any F or B turns or D turns
只要魔方那好不要乱转,这三个面都可以转的很顺手,也不比转动前面和后面
so it's very physically efficient and very comfortable
顺手又高效
so that's another very interesting part of the zz method
zz解法就是这样任性!!
after you solve the F2L, you'll get a cross on the top here
做完F2L,顶层会出现个十字(译者:因为第一步把色相都弄好了,这可很爽啊,要知道CFOP的OLL的第一步就是这个十字)
this will resemble ... what happens after  you say  you do  a two look OLL and you solve the cross it will automaticall solve for you
这感觉...就像做OLL(顶层色相还原)时,第一步的顶层十字不用做就自动好了(译者:我前面说了吧:)
if you dont know OLL .. you will soon
不懂OLL... 你很快会懂的
if you use the zz method because you'll get an automaticall top cross
用zz解法顶层十字自动会完成,
and those seven (COLLs?) will act as one look oll which is very cool
所以COLL(底层色相还原的第二步:还原角块色相)就可以一眼看穿了(译者:我还没这程度)
if you're like (light weight ous?)
如果你是某某高手的话(译者:高手教我!!)
it really restrict your last layer
PLL(顶层一步还原)的情况就少多了
speaking of restricting your last layer
说到限制顶层的情况
the top cross also serves as a said way into  more case restriction, if you want to do sort of one look last layer
如果想要玩顶层一步法,有顶层十字的限制,情况也会才很多
some people.. because you have already form the top cross, go even further in restricting  the cases of last layer by say.. permuting edges or orienting corners
有人更进一步,不单单限制顶层的情况,还完成了顶层边块位置还原或者角块色相的还原
makes one-look last layer more practical
这样一眼看穿顶层的PLL情况就更具可行性了
so that's pretty much breakdown of  the zz method. the steps are again:  EO line;  F2L and last layer
zz解法大概就这样.复习下: EO线(所有边块色相还原+"底面一条柴"(译者:'我爱一条柴'!!^_^)) ; F2L(下面两层); 最后一层
the last layer has variety of options, you can even do some very interesting last slot tricks like CLS or (winter?) variation
最后一层的解决各种各样,你也可以玩玩各种"空槽)CLS( 译者:大概就是F2L只完成三个槽,剩一个空槽可以做缓冲, 灵活很多,这个空槽完成时候, 顶层的情况也少)
those are more common and easy because edges are oriented and you dont have to do say (els?) in order to orient the edges before you do cls
因为所有边块色相都还原好了,所以玩"空槽"就相对简单多了
so in case you're a bit comfused by the terminology, I'll have links in the description
这些"术语"是不是吓到你了,迷惑了? 我会留下链接的(译者:我就不留了,自己随便找都有.如果有美女不懂的话,12点以后到我房间,我们"深入"探讨WX: alison1999)
so you guys can see all the algorithm sets I'm talking about
链接里有各种公式
so like winter variation ,cls I'll link you guys to all of those so you guys can see what all of those's all about
各种公式各种情况,自个玩去吧
let's get down to the demonstrations
下面就是实例演示了
all right. so let's take a look at  this scramble it's actually sitting in front of me for quite a while now
好,我们想看看这个打乱的魔方,都已经放我前面好久了(译者:蠢蠢欲动啊,哪个部位?!)
I'm going to solve this, and show you guys what a zz solve will look like
要解开咯,各位看清楚zz
I'm going to just solve the EO line ,point it out to you just  to show you what it's like, solve the F2L
我会先完成第一步EO线,指给你看好,
point it out to you to show you what its like, and then solve the last layer and then talk a little bit and then will be fine
第二步的F2L也是完成后指给你看好,第三步完成顶层就还原魔方了. 之后再讲些有意思的东西
in terms of the demonstration solve
这样zz的解法就讲完了
here is what I'll do for the EO line
这里我先完成EO线
like that
像这样
and the line is solved
就解决了
can see the line?
看到没?这条线
and the edgs are oriented. dont worry if you cant tell they're oriented
所有的边块色相也调好了.现在看不懂边块色相是不是调好没关系
there will be plenty of video content for you guys to watch and I'll be teaching edge orientation in  a very very  comprehensive manner.
视频教程陆续有来的! 下一集的调好边块色相我会讲的很详细的(译者:真的很详细! 2,4,6,8,10,12,我都快睡着了!^_^)
as of now , I finished this EO line. so now what I'm  here on is F2L
好,第一步完工,第二步F2L
so I'm gonna solve the F2L using  three (joints) so no cube rotation required
我只用三相就可以完成下面两层,不用整体转动魔方哦
it's only RUL so keep an eye on that
我的操作只用转动RUL(顶层右面左面),看好哦
and it's not solved HAHA
还没好 哈哈哈(译者:^_^)
this is what we calle a CLS
这就是CLS(译者: corner last slot? 空槽)
and I was mention it earlier but
之前我提到过
there is an algorithm set  that  flip all this corners
有个公式可以翻转这些角块
If you have only one corner misplaced
如果只有一个角块不对的话,可以用那公式
on the F2L and the rest is done
其他都好了
so what I'm gonna do is flip this corner and  flip the other corners
我现在要翻转这个角块和其他的角块
the algorithm goes like this
用公式这样转
it give us OLL
做完就是OLL了(顶层色相还原)
bucause all the corners are fliped
因为所有角块都翻转好了(色相对了)
and all the edges are fliped in the first place
而一开始的边块色相就已经调好了
so It allow me to do that
所以结果就是OLL了
like that
像这样
and the cube is solved.
魔方就还原好了
so that was a pretty normal zz solve minus CLS
这就是zz解法,没有用到"空槽"
CLS doesnt technically belong in the zz method but It's certainly very handy
空槽不算zz解法,但很方便
because It allows you to skip steps and maybe even combines two steps together
因为有些步骤可以省略甚至两步合并
so I highly recommand learning it , I'll cover  some  general CLS stuff
所以我强烈推荐去学. 以后我也会讲解些空槽
in future video in the series
在以后的这个视频教程系列讲解
but for now that was the demonstration of I hope you guys enjoy what zz look like
那这就是实例演示了.希望你喜欢zz解法
if you are interested we can continue to the method history
如果看得有趣,我们接着讲讲zz解决的由来
all right, so let's talk about the history of the method
好,下面讲讲zz解法的由来
so this method was invented in 2006 by a man named Zbigniew Zborowski
zz解法是由zz(译者:这个得好好找找,不能让人家吃亏)Zbigniew Zborowski 在2006年发明的
I aksed one of polish friends had it  pronouced and he say it was vaguely that
我问了我一个波兰朋友发音,额,大概是那样,
so in the future I'm just gonna  call him zz or Mr.Z
以后提到他老人家我就叫他zz或者Z先辈了
so as I said earlier this method  was invented in 2006
我刚说了zz在2006年发明
and when it was being proposed and developed, It had ergonomics in mind
and when it was being proposed and developed, It had ergonomics in mind
and when I said ergonomics in plaint english It means the study / the science of making things comfortable and efficient
"人体工程"?在英语里就是研究让人身体上更舒适的学科(译者:我说这词我怎么知道,原来有所谓的人体工程学键盘,因为有RSI(重复性肌腱劳损))
so if you were to play ergonomics type of thinking to more practical thing such as cup
比如说杯子
a more ergonomic cup It would be easier to hold while you're walking
一个"人体工程"杯子会在人走路的时候更好拿
like the shape of the cup would be easier to hold so you dont spill while you're walking somewhere
比如设计杯子的形状让它不会在人走路的时候撒出液体
or perhaps the material of the cup would be not so susceptible to temperature change
或者杯子的材质更耐热
let's say you're driking something really really hot, you wouldnt burn your hand while drinking it
喝热东西的时候不会烫伤手
so that's ergonomics in the conventional sense, in the 3x3 zz solve ergonomics as limiting cube rotations
现实生活的例子就是类似这样. zz解法就是符合人体工程学的解法,它不用整体转动三阶魔方
and restricting your F2L to RUL moves
而且把F2L下面两层的还原只需要用更舒适的RUL转动即可
so that was his point of view of what ergonomics was on his cube and I think he persuit it very very well thought out in high level degree
这就是zz先辈在"如何更舒适地玩魔方"这点上的理解,我觉得他的理解很好也很好地在zz解法里实践了!
in developing the zz method so that's what ergonomics refers to
这就是魔方里的"人体工程学"
right now the zz method is (lump) together with three other methods in a group called "the big four"
目前zz解法和其他三种解法并称魔方还原"大老四"
and those are just totally  informal
呵呵,只是戏称,别太当真
but 'the big four' are the methods most people know about
但"大老四"这说法大部分人都知道(译者: 至今从没见过会玩魔方的人,更别提女人了!泪....)
they don't know how to necessarily do every single thing in the method they know they exist
不必每个步骤都知道,知道有就行了
they know other people out there are practicing them
肯定有其他人练这个解法
they are competitive with those methods
速拧解法各有千秋
the big four methods include CFOP (perture?) (rul?) and zz
这"大老四"包括CFOP(译者:这个熟的很, cross F2L OLL PLL 首字母) OO XX 还有zz
however dispite being a 'big four method', I think zz is still relatively unexplored compared to other method such as CFOP which has been studied over and over again
可惜虽然身为"大老四"的一员,zz受到的关注和发展明显远远不如CFOP,CFOP都快被研究得地朝天了
and a lot of people use it. so I think zz should definitely get more of chance to be seen in the world
用CFOP的人也多, 我觉得zz解法应该让更多的人知道它的存在
that's part of reason why I was making this tutorial
这就是我做这个视频教程的一部分原因
to show everyone what  the method is all about so people who are interested in switching have an opportunity to expore a new method
让人们了解zz解法,让想换魔方解法的人有机会接触这个新的解法
so that pretty much does it for the history of the method
那,zz解法的由来差不多就讲到这里了
after that one I'm gonna talk about my experience using it
下面是我的个人体会
all right. so for those of you  who dont know me very well , My name is Phil Yu
还有人不认识我,我的名字是Phil Yu
I've been solving with the zz method since 2009
我从2009年起就用zz解法还原魔方了
I first came across the method in the speed sovling forum
我第一次遇见zz解法是在"速拧"论坛(译者:如果没错的话https://www.speedsolving.com/)
I just read the thread and on the thread there was some guy post a  text documentation of the method
我看到一帖子,有人用文档描述了此解法
so the first description of the method I got was in text so I  read the whole thing  and I was really interested
所以我第一次遇到zz解法是看文字版的,我看完后觉得很有趣
because It was a whole new way to kind of look at efficiency when solving
因为这是个全新的高效的速拧解法
so I was really interested
我真的很感兴趣
I felt that It had great one-handed potential
我觉得用它单拧的效率也很不错
and It really went along with the things I prefer for one-handed
zz解法和我偏爱的单拧也融合得不错
so the efficiency that was inbeded in the method
zz解法内含的高效
was also the efficiency I prefered in  one-hand solving those so I thought those two will wok well together
和我偏爱的单拧的高效手法相映得彰
so I tried that I still solve zz today
所以我就尝试了,然后直到现在
and I'm very happy I do
我很庆幸
because A: It sets me apart B it's like an adventure
因为1. 这让我显得特别 2. 这就像是场冒险
because I don't know what I'm going to do next with the method
因为我不知道用这个解法下一步会怎样
there's always new things to learn
总有新鲜事物可以学习
It's really interesting to be one of the first people to use the method competitively
成为第一个用此法玩速拧的人很有趣我喜欢
as of 20:12 right now it's 20:12 in  recording this video I average around 11 seconds two-handed 13 seconds one-handed
现在是晚上8点12分,录这个视频时我的双手速度平均11秒, 单拧平均13秒
and even though 13s one-haned seems a bit fast
虽然13秒的单拧成绩看起来很快了
I think there's definitely room for growth
我觉得还有进步的空间
I definitely feel like I could do a lot of things better than I currently do
我真的觉得还有很多东西可以做的比现在更好
I'm really excited to see where the method will go in the future which is part of the reason why I'm making this video
我真的想看看zz解法将来会如何发展,这也是我做此视频教程的一部分原因
I'm making it so that more people can see how the method works
希望此视频让更多人了解zz解法
perhaps more people can make the mothod their own method
也许更多人就能换用此解法还原魔方了
you know I feel like this process has really great mutual benefit effect
我觉得这个过程是互利互惠的
which I'm going to explain right now
下面我觉解释为什么会对双方都有利
so the effect I was describing earlier
我刚说的互利互惠大概是这样
kind of goes like this so you get a new method and you learn how it basically work
你学了一个新的还原魔方的方法
you kind of work it in with your own style and your preferences
你把这个方法和自己原有的方法结合
and because the mothod has been tested already I'm sure if you go about it  the right way
因为这个解法已经被证实是有效的,所以如果你学法的当应该没问题学的会
you'll get some great times and you'll experience a whole new way of solving a cube which to me is very stimulating
学习的过程有乐趣,你会体验到全新的解法,这我喜欢!
so you'll get all those results
所以你学会了zz解法
and then what you can do is you take all the things you find and give back to the method
然后你可以把你学会的东西在反补到这个zz解法上
and you know all this interesting techniques you find
有趣的公式啦步骤啦
maybe you find some algorithms or you know you find a  way to build  blocks in a really cool way you just give it back to the method
或者"筑基"的新方法,这些反补到zz解法上
and the method will keep growing and growing
zz解法就这样发展了
and  you'll grow as solver as you use the method and the method will grow with you
你用zz解法还原魔方你学到了,而zz解法因此也发展了
which is the really really cool thing about using a new method
这样的互利互惠不是很cool的一件事吗?
personally , I don't find it the same  if the method's just  all developed just like laid out in front of you
这是那些已经发展完备的解法不能比拟的,没有自己发展的空间,一切都有先人探索过好好地摆在你面前了
I personally like to interact with my method
我个人喜欢参与到我的解法
so I think zz is really really great for that
所以我觉得zz解法非常好
so I'm hoping more people can see this tutorial and get a better idea of what zz is all about
所以我喜欢越来越多的人看到此教程,学到zz解法
I'm currently one of the only competitive zz solvers out there
我是目前唯一的一个用此解法玩速拧的人(译者:不要觉得作者洋洋得意.这视频教程我不知道是多久的了!而且人家成绩摆在那)
and I definitely wish there were more
我真心希望有更多人用此法
so if you're interested I hope to see you in the next video
那,如果你对此法感兴趣,我希望下个视频教程见到你
the next video will be a video of  edge orientation detection and that will become the first educational portion of the series
下一集是关于边块色相判断正确与否,也是本系列第一个真正的学习教程
I'll teach you how to detect all the wrong edges you can eventually orient them
我会教你如何判定边块色相以便你可以调整正确
so that's what you'll look out afterwards
这是后面的内容了
if you're still curious about the method and  want to see more I have plenty of solving videos that I'll post in the description
如果你是个好奇的宝宝, 我后面还有更多的视频教程,其他资料也放到下面的链接里了
as well as some walk through solves if you're interested  in the thought process involved in the zz method
还有完整的实例以及每个步骤的想法
so thanks again for watching the video I hope to see you in the next part
感谢观看此视频,希望下个视频还能看到你